# ÁLVARO PERIS

Machine learning engineer/data scientist. I hold a PhD in computer science, involving the use of deep learning for sequence-to-sequence modeling, human–computer interaction, system adaptation and multimodality. I published my research in international conferences and journals and open-sourced toolkits for NMT and visual captioning.

As a machine learning engineer, I worked in startup environments, developing and deploying machine learning systems, related to speech recognition, NLP and document analysis. I enjoy tackling challenging problems, analyzing and deploying effective solutions to them. I also like monitoring current systems, evaluating metrics and continuously improving them.

## Professional Experience

2019 - 2020	Sonia Labs.
	Machine learning engineer.
2015 - 2019	PRHLT Research Center, Universitat Politècnica de València.
	Researcher (superior technician).
2014 - 2015	PRHLT Research Center, Universitat Politècnica de València.
	Student researcher.

#### **EDUCATION**

2015 - 2019 PhD in Computer Science.

Universitat Politècnica de València.

EXCELLENT CUM LAUDE.

2014 – 2015 MSc in Artificial Intelligence, Pattern Recognition

AND DIGITAL IMAGING.

Universitat Politècnica de València.

GPA: 9.2/10.

2008 - 2014 BSc in Computer Engineering.

Universitat Politècnica de València.

GPA: 7.5/10.

#### LANGUAGES

Spanish Mother tongue.

Catalan Full professional competence.

ENGLISH Advanced (Cambridge Advanced English Certificate).

GERMAN Beginner.

#### TECHNICAL SKILLS

Programming languages I Machine learning expertise I Machine learning libraries I Other I

Python, Java, UNIX shell scripting, Matlab, Haskell. Deep learning, NLP, CV, seq2seq, document analysis. Tensorflow, PyTorch, Keras, Theano, Scikit-learn, Pandas. Git, CI/CD, Bazel, Docker and Kubernetes (limited expertise).

## OPEN SOURCE LIBRARIES

NMT-Keras Fully-fledged neural machine translation toolkit.

Interactive Keras Captioning Interactive multimedia captioning.

ABiViRNet Neural video captioning.

sentence-selectioNN Neural sentence classifiers, for data selection.

VIBIKNet Visual question answering.

TMA Egocentric video captioning with extended context.

#### SCIENTIFIC COMMITTEES

Served as reviewer for several journals, including: Information Processing & Management, Machine Translation Journal, Language Resources and Evaluation.

# SCIENTIFIC PUBLICATIONS (SELECTION)

- Álvaro Peris. Interactivity, Adaptation and Multimodality in Neural Sequence-to-sequence Learning. PhD dissertation, 2019.
- Álvaro Peris and Francisco Casacuberta. A Neural, Interactive-predictive System for Multimodal Sequence to Sequence Tasks. In *Proceedings of the Annual Meeting of the Association for Computational Linguistics (ACL), System Demonstrations*, pp. 81–86, 2019.
- Miguel Domingo, Mercedes García-Martínez, Álvaro Peris, Alexandre Helle, Amando Estela, Laurent Bié, Francisco Casacuberta and Manuel Herranz. Incremental Adaptation of NMT for Professional Post-editors: A User Study. In Proceedings of Machine Translation Summit XVII Volume 2: Translator, Project and User Tracks, pp. 219–227, 2019.
- Álvaro Peris and Francisco Casacuberta. Online learning for effort reduction in interactive neural machine translation. In *Computer Speech & Language*, vol. 58, pp. 98–126, 2019.
- Álvaro Peris and Francisco Casacuberta. Active Learning for Interactive Neural Machine Translation of Data Streams. In *Proceedings of the 22nd Conference on Computational Natural Language Learning (CoNLL)*, pp. 151–160, 2018.
- Marc Bolaños, **Álvaro Peris** and Francisco Casacuberta, Sergi Soler y Petia Radeva. Egocentric Video Description based on Temporally-Linked Sequences. In *Journal of Visual Communication and Image Representation*, vol. 50 pp. 205-216, 2018.
- Álvaro Peris and Francisco Casacuberta. NMT-Keras: a Very Flexible Toolkit with a Focus on Interactive NMT and Online Learning. *The Prague Bulletin of Mathematical Linguistics*, vol. 111 pp. 113-124, 2018.
- Álvaro Peris, Mara Chinea-Ríos, and Francisco Casacuberta. Neural Networks Classifier for Data Selection in Statistical Machine Translation. In *The Prague Bulletin of Mathematical Linguistics*, vol. 108, pp. 283–294, 2017.
- Álvaro Peris, Miguel Domingo and Francisco Casacuberta. Interactive Neural Machine Translation. In *Computer Speech & Language*, vol. 45, pp. 201–220, 2017.
- Álvaro Peris, Marc Bolaños, Petia Radeva, and Francisco Casacuberta. Video Description using Bidirectional Recurrent Neural Networks. In *Proceedings of the 25th ICANN*, vol 2, pp. 3–11. 2016.
- $\rightarrow$  Full list of publications.